Finding Aid for Department of Communication (University of Michigan) records, 1926-1995
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Department of Communication (University of Michigan) records 1926-1995
University of Michigan. Department of Communications.
(in 10 boxes)
9.3 linear feet
87124 Bimu C26 2
Formerly called the Department of Journalism; includes administrative files, records of sponsored workshops, conferences, and lectures; faculty personnel files; and records of internship programs, including reports from students interning at local Michigan newspapers.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The record group (Donor No. 1674 ) has come to the library in periodic accessions since the early 1970s. Some of the files were accessioned through Professor John Stevens (Donor No. 4666 ).
Periodic additions to the records expected.
The record group is open to research without restriction.
The Department of Communication came into existence on July 1, 1979 as a result of a merger between the Department of Journalism and the speech component of the Department of Speech Communication and Theatre. This merger represented the culmination of almost a decade of discussion.
In the early 1970s some members of both predecessor departments noted significant overlaps within the two unit's missions, prompting discussions regarding the possibility of a departmental merger. These discussions received considerable impetus in 1974 when the College of Literature, Science, and the Arts (LS&A) Performance Evaluation Committee took official notice of the two departments' similarities and recommended the possibility of a merger be seriously explored. In 1975 the LS&A College Priorities Committee noted the Performance Evaluation Committee's suggestions, and reaffirmed the importance of serious merger discussions. The Department of Journalism moved quickly to implement the committee's recommendations, and by the Spring of 1977 had put forward a formal merger proposal. The Department of Speech Communication and Theatre was, however, unconvinced that a sufficient rationale existed to justify a merger and, while open to discussion, put forward no merger plan of its own. Finally, in early 1978, as LS&A dean Billy Frye announced his plans to establish a special faculty committee to examine the situation, the Department of Speech Communication and Theater offered for discussion its own merger plan.
A major concern of the Speech Communication and Theater departmental leadership was the possible dismemberment of the department in any merger. The department as constituted had three major components: speech and hearing sciences, theatre, and speech communication. Sentiment for an independent theater department was strong. As early as 1974 individuals involved in theatre work had suggested the formation of an independent department. LS&A's College Priorities Committee, while acknowledging that the speech and hearing sciences component of the department was first rate, had concluded that it was an area of study that did not really belong among the humanities. The clear implication was that in any major departmental restructuring this element of the program would likely be spun off into a new "scientific" home. Journalism's primary interest was in merging only with the speech communication component of the department. Thus Speech Communication and Theater, as an existing entity, could foresee little gain but much loss in any department merger.
In October 1978 the special committee appointed by Dean Frye submitted a terse report in which it generally recommended the division of the existing speech department along the lines feared by Speech. The committee concluded that sentiment for a separate theatre department had grown so strong that its establishment seemed certain. The committee recommended that the remaining two components of the department be located in other departments through a process of mutual negotiation, with the speech communication element to be merged with an expanded and renamed Journalism Department. In January 1979 Dean Frye informed the faculties of the Speech Communication and Theater Department and the journalism department of his intention to recommend to the Regents formal action along the lines outlined by the special committee. In March 1979 the Regents heard and accepted the dean's report, authorizing the establishment of two new departments within LS&A, the Department of Communication and the Department of Theater and Drama.
While the Regent's action formally resolved the structural issues, there was still at issue a question of the centrality of the new Department of Communication to the basic mission of LS&A. While the excellence of the program offered through the department was generally acknowledged, the LS&A College Priorities Committee, in 1975, had stated that, "[The CPC] does not regard Journalism as of central importance in a liberal arts education." The fundamental question facing the new department, then, was not a matter of demonstrating its excellence, but rather in demonstrating its importance to the humanities. The arena for the continuing discussion of this issue was the budgetary reduction process of the early 1980s. Communication had lost several tenure track positions as a result of the merger, and in the next few years three more tenure track positions were lost as a result of budgetary considerations. While the department survived, it did so in a somewhat reduced form.
In 1995, a review committee evaluated the future of the graduate-level journalism degree program and recommended that a Certificate in Journalism be explored. The committee also recommended that the Masters in Journalism degree program within LS&A not be relocated and that a moratorium be placed on admissions to the program in the Fall of 1996. The recommendations followed an earlier faculty committee which advised that the Department of Communication be restructured for undergraduate and doctoral study of mass communication. The resulting Department of Communication Studies was intended to focus on the study of the process of mass communication, rather than the preparation of journalists.
The Department of Communication record group consists of ten linear feet of records dating from 1926 to 1995 and processed in four accessions. The pre-1984 accessions document the Department of Journalism. The 1984 accession includes materials accumulated by professor Marion Marzolf. The 1986 accession represents records created through the merger of Journalism with Speech and the records of the new department's chairman after the merger was accomplished. The 1996 accession contains material similar to the earlier accessions with the exception of material relating to the graduate Master in Journalism degree program and the decision to suspend the program.
The original accession (Boxes 1-5) documents Department of Journalism activity from 1928 to 1981 (primarily 1950-1970). The accession has been divided into three series: Administrative Files; Faculty Personnel Records; and Internships, Fellowships and Scholarships.
The 1984 accession consists of three series of records: those from a 1977 conference, "Kerner Plus 10: Minorities and the Media," those from the University of Michigan student chapter of Kappa Tau Alpha, and those from the student chapter of Women in Communications, Inc. (WICI). Both the Kerner conference records and the WICI records reflect the involvement of Professor Marion T. Marzolf in the Department of Communication.
The 1986 accession dates from 1964 to 1986 (primarily 1975-1984). It represents the records kept by Peter Clarke, last chairman of the Department of Journalism and first chairman of the Department of Communication, the files of William E. Porter, who served as chair after Clarke's resignation in 1981, and a few documents of John D. Stevens, who succeeded Porter in 1984. The accession has been divided into two series, Chairman's Correspondence (1964-1985) and a Topical File (1949-1986).
Subjects:
Adrian daily telegram.; Ann Arbor news.; Battle Creek enquirer and news.; Bay City times.; Benton Harbor news-palladium.; Clinton County republican news.; Detroit Free Press.; Detroit news.; Detroit times.; Flint journal.; Grand Haven daily tribune.; Grand Rapids herald (1892); Grand Rapids press.; Holland evening sentinel.; Ionia sentinel-standard.; Kalamazoo gazette.; Lansing state journal.; Niles daily star.; Owosso argus press.; Pontiac press.; Port Huron times herald.; Royal Oak daily tribune.; Saginaw news.; Evening news (Sault Sainte Marie, Mich.); Kerner Plus 10 Conference (1977: University of Michigan); Kappa Tau Alpha.; Women in Communications, Inc.; University of Michigan--Congresses.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Communication.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Journalism.; Journalists--Michigan.; American newspapers--Michigan.; Whitehall (Mich.); Hayden, Tom.; Ann Arbor (Mich.); Detroit (Mich.); Evart (Mich.)
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Fires.; Haven Hall (University of Michigan: 1863-1950); University of Michigan. Dept. of Communication.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Journalism.; University of Michigan--Faculty.
Contributors:
Clarke, Peter.; Gingrich, Arnold.; Hersey, John, 1914-1993.; Mailer, Norman.; Porter, William Earl.; Marzolf, Marion.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Administrative Files 1945-1981
  The Administrative Files have three subseries: General (1945-1981), Lectures, Conferences and Workshops (1928-1979) and Department Research (1950-1964).
  - General 1945-1981
    The General subseries consists of accreditation reports, course records, curriculum reports, reports and records regarding the merger of the Department of Journalism with the Department of Speech in 1979, and other miscellaneous administrative documents. These records are of most value for studying changes made in the academic program since the 1950s and for understanding the reasons for the merger.
    - Accreditation Reports 1953-1967 (Box 1)
    - Correspondence
      - General 1957-1973 (Box 1)
      - Swinton, Stanley circa 1951 (Box 1)
      - White, Lee (Detroit News), 1950 (Box 1)
    - Courses
      - 105,1950 (Box 1)
      - 141,1949-1950 (Box 1)
      - 290,1955-1956 (Box 1)
      - 301,1950 (Box 1)
      - 407 (formally 141),1953-1964 (Box 1)
      - 408 (formally 142),1954-1964 (Box 1)
    - Curriculum Reports
      - 1953, 1967 (Box 1)
      - 1977-1981 (Box 1)
    - Departmental Philosophy 1972 (Box 1)
    - Faculty Meeting Minutes 1950-1952 (Box 1)
    - Graduate Program 1948-1954 (Box 1)
    - Junior College Programs 1950, 1971-1972 (Box 1)
    - Merger, Departments of Journalism and Speech 1977-1979 (Box 1)
    - Michigan Daily, Physical Plant Improvements 1945-1948 (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous (includes Howard Kahn's analysis of student newspapers, 1969) (Box 1)
    - Writer in Residence Committee 1965-1966 (Box 1)
  - Lectures, Conferences and Workshops 1928-1979
    The Lectures, Conferences and Workshops subseries consists primarily of correspondence, programs and publicity notes on the various extra-curricular activities of the Journalism department. The Research subseries is divided into three units, one regarding sources of funding, the second actual research, and third a general category. Actual or proposed funding sources include the Carnegie Foundation, the Ford Foundation, the Readers Digest Travel Fund, and the Rockefeller Foundation.
    - General
      - Lists of Lectures, Conferences and Workshops 1947-1968 (Box 1)
      - 1928-1940 (Box 1)
      - 1947-1948 (Box 1)
      - 1949-1956 (Box 1)
      - 1964-1969 (Box 1)
      - 1978-1979 (Box 1)
    - Specific Conferences
      - High School Newspaper Workshops 1954-1961 (Box 2)
      - "Future of the Fourth Estate," 1967 (Box 2)
      - Tax Conference 1977 (Box 2)
      - "Libel and the Press," 1978 (Box 2)
      - "Privacy and the Press," 1978 (Box 2)
  - Departmental Research 1950-1964
    Departmental Research project material includes correspondence, surveys and reports dated between 1950 and 1959. Of particular interest was the Evart project (1956) in which students managed a small Michigan newspaper. A history of Whitehall, Michigan is also included in this unit. The third unit, general, contains miscellaneous information about the research program, a few student papers, and letters to newspaper editors throughout Michigan written by the Department of Journalism seeking new research ideas.
    - Funding
      - Carnegie Foundation 1952 (Box 2)
      - Ford Foundation
        - Proposal 1952 (Box 2)
        - Survey of Behavioral Sciences 1953-1954 (Box 2)
        - Research in the Professional Schools 1953-1954 (Box 2)
        - Public Relations Research 1958-1959 (Box 2)
        - Proposals for Improving Journalism Schools 1964 (Box 2)
      - Readers Digest Travel Fund 1956-1967 (Box 2)
      - Rockefeller Foundation 1952 (Box 2)
    - Projects
      - Analysis of the Interchange of News Between the U.S. and Canada
        - Papers 1950-1951 (Box 2)
        - Reports 1951 (Box 2)
        - Miscellaneous 1950-1952 (Box 2)
      - Study of Teacher Supply, Demand and Placement 1954 (Box 2)
      - Smoking Survey 1955 (Box 2)
      - Ann Arbor Housing 1955 (Box 2)
      - Impact of the News Media in Ann Arbor 1955 (Box 2)
      - Impact of the News Media in Ann Arbor 1956 (Box 2)
      - Evart Weekly Project 1956 (Box 2)
      - Detroit Newspaper Strike 1957 (Box 2)
      - Whitehall, Michigan 1959 (Box 2)
    - General
      - Research Program 1949-1957 (Box 2)
      - Student Papers (Box 2)
      - Letters to Newspaper Editors Seeking Suggestions 1957 (Box 2)
- Faculty Personnel Files 1943-1972
  Faculty Personnel Records consists of vitas and other materials relating to the employment of staff members. This series is arranged alphabetically and covers the approximate periods of 1943 to 1970.
  - Brumm, John L. 1945-1958 (Box 3)
  - Chatters, Kenneth 1950-1952 (Box 3)
  - Drury, W. Edward 1966-1970 (Box 3)
  - Haines, Donal 1943-1951 (Box 3)
  - Howell, Joseph 1961-1962 (Box 3)
  - Lee, Alfred M. 1947-1948 (Box 3)
  - Lindstrom, Carl 1956-1965 (Box 3)
  - Maurer, Wesley H. 1967-1970 (Box 3)
  - Mullendore, William H. 1958 (Box 3)
  - Payne, Jay H. 1951-1954 (Box 3)
  - Prakken, Lawrence 1948-1951 (Box 3)
  - Shoenfield, Allen 1968-1969 (Box 3)
  - Sneider, Vernon J. 1966-1967 (Box 3)
  - Stanger, Eck 1948-1952 (Box 3)
  - Stoneman, William H. 1968-1969 (Box 3)
  - Tendler, Louis 1948-1949 (Box 3)
  - Wegmann, Earl 1948-1949 (Box 3)
  - White, Ink 1948-1951 (Box 3)
  - Wooding, Edmund 1949-1969 (Box 3)
  - Zeisler, Karl F. 1948-1972 (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous 1948-1965 (Box 3)
- Internships, Fellowships, and Scholarships 1947-1969
  Internships, Fellowships, and Scholarships has two subseries; administrative files and student files. The administrative file includes correspondence, program descriptions, lists, and other papers concerning the program in general. Most of these materials relate to the University Press Club Fellowships (foreign student internships) and Post BA and MA Journalism training fellowships (American students). The student files have been arranged alphabetically under the two major internships programs mentioned above. The student reports are most interesting as they contain the students' comments about Michigan newspapers and the communities where they interned. There is one file of special note on Tom Hayden, a founder and leader of the Students for a Democratic Society (SDS).
  A large number of additional student papers prepared by Journalism students have been cataloged separately under the heading: University of Michigan. Department of Journalism. A finding aid exists describing these records.
  - Administrative Files
    - Cumulative Lists of Interns 1947-1965 (Box 3)
    - Correspondence with the Graduate School (Box 3)
    - Prospects for Internships (Box 3)
    - University Press Club Fellows: Foreign Student Internships 1947-1966
      - General Information 1947-1966 (Box 3)
      - Forms and Procedures 1958-1959 (Box 3)
      - Press Club Committee for Selection 1952-1960 (Box 3)
    - Journalism Training Fellowships: American Students 1947-1966
      - Description of Programs 1947-1966 (Box 3)
      - Administrative Correspondence 1957-1961 (Box 3)
      - Papers Concerning Internal Revenue Service Ruling 1957-1958 (Box 3)
      - Visitation Reports 1957 (Box 3)
      - Visitation Reports 1958-1959 (Box 3)
      - Visitation Reports 1960-1961 (Box 3)
    - Scholarships
      - Brumm, John L., Scholarship Fund 1956-1967 (Box 3)
      - Campbell, Chester M. Endowment Funds 1957-1968 (Box 3)
      - Chamberlin. A. Winthrop B., Scholarships 1953 (Box 3)
      - Jenkins, Guy H., Memorial Scholarship Funds 1960 (Box 3)
      - McDonald, Glenn, Scholarship 1960 (Box 3)
      - National Endowment for Humanities Fellowships 1973-1974 (Box 4)
      - WJR Inc. Scholarships 1972-1973 (Box 4)
    - Internships
      - Campbell Ewald Summer Internships 1957-1961 (Box 4)
      - Radio and Television Internships 1965-1966 (Box 4)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 4)
  - Student Reports and Papers 1947-1969
    - University Press Club Fellows: Foreign Student Internships 1947-1962
      - Abdou, Saad El-Dine 1955-1957 (Reports) (Box 4)
      - Abdou, Saad El-Dine 1955-1957 (Papers) (Box 4)
      - Adam, Lefteri C. 1953-1954 (Box 4)
      - Azhar, Ali Khan 1957-1959 (Reports) (Box 4)
      - Azhar, Ali Khan 1957-1959 (Reports) (Box 4)
      - Bailyn, Inez K. Perrson 1951-1952 (Box 4)
      - Barison, Alvise 1949-1952 (Box 4)
      - Bergqvist, Jaake 1960 (Box 4)
      - Besselink, Herman 1954-1956 (Reports) (Box 4)
      - Besselink, Herman 1954-1956 (Papers) (Box 4)
      - Chakravorti, Robindra 1954-1956, 2 folders (Box 4)
      - Gapper, S. Gordon 1953-1956 (Box 4)
      - Gervaso, Guisseppe Roberto 1960 (Box 4)
      - Greiss, Lewis 1957-1959 (Box 4)
      - Holmes, George 1954-1956 (Box 4)
      - Kim, Yong Hyun 1956-1958 (Reports) (Box 4)
      - Kim, Yong Hyun 1956-1958 (Papers) (Box 4)
      - Lee, Wono 1957-1959 (Reports) (Box 4)
      - Lee, Wono 1957-1959 (Papers) (Box 4)
      - Marull-Perretta, Horacio 1958-1960 (Box 4)
      - Mrowa, Dounia 1952-1966 (Box 4)
      - Ntoampe, Theodore S. 1959-1964 (Box 5)
      - Padel, Gerd 1948-1950 (Box 5)
      - Rodriquez, Manuel Eduardo 1951-1953 (Box 5)
      - Rojnik, Albert 1950-1952 (Box 5)
      - Sanchez, Emma 1957 (Box 5)
      - Sasaki, Ken-Ichi 1958-1960 (Box 5)
      - Soucek, Rudolf 1948-1950 (Box 5)
      - Stumpf, Hanns M. 1949-1951 (Box 5)
      - Tanaka, Junichi 1959-1962 (Box 5)
      - Yacoub, George 1953-1954 (Box 5)
      - Zwicker, Barrie 1958-1961 (Box 5)
    - Journalism Training Fellowships: American Students
      - Bow, James W. 1960 (Box 5)
      - Cain, Stephen B. 1963-1964 (Box 5)
      - Chapin, Darlene 1959-1960 (Box 5)
      - Elliot, Eleanor K. 1959-1961 (Box 5)
      - Elly, Edward A. 1958-1959 (Box 5)
      - Emmert, John 1964-1966 (Box 5)
      - Gibson, G. Thomas 1967-1969 (Box 5)
      - Good, David 1966 (Box 5)
      - Gongwer, Sharon 1962 (Box 5)
      - Gover, Raymond L. 1958-1960 (Box 5)
      - Granstrom, June circa 1954 (Box 5)
      - Hanninen, Oliver 1954-1955 (Box 5)
      - Hayden, Thomas
        - Papers 1962-1964 (Box 5)
        - Paper 1964 entitled, "Radical Nomad: Essays on Wright Mills and his Times" (Box 5)
        - Paper 1963 entitled, "The New Possibilities for Peace" (Box 5)
      - Kaul, Donald 1960-1961 (Box 5)
      - Mathews, Cleve circa 1949 (Box 5)
      - Myers, Barbara 1955-1957 (Box 5)
      - Neal, Jack 1960 (Box 5)
      - Patrick, June C. 1956-1957 (Box 5)
      - Peterson, Kenneth L. 1952 (Reports) (Box 5)
      - Peterson, Kenneth L. 1951-1957 (Papers) (Box 5)
      - Reynolds, Richard 1964-1965 (Box 5)
      - Reynolds, Roy 1957 (Box 5)
      - Thomas, Don 1949-1953 (Box 5)
      - Warren, Robert L. 1947 (Box 5)
- "Kerner plus 10: Minorities and the Media," 1977 conference
  "Kerner Plus 10," held on April 22, 1977, was sponsored by the Department of Journalism's Howard R. Marsh Center for the Study of Journalistic Performance. Professor Marzolf was one of the planners and directors of the conference, which examined the question of minority representation in the media ten years after the Kerner Commission. The original Kerner Commission was established following the Detroit riots of 1967, and delivered an indictment directed at racism in the American news media. This series includes a published conference report as well as a transcript of the proceedings. Of special interest are the questionnaire responses from Black and Chicano news professionals concerning the situation in individual work places.
  - Articles and Publications (Box 6)
  - Kerner plus 10 (published report) (Box 6)
  - Letters (Box 6)
  - Marsh Requests (Box 6)
  - Proceedings (Box 6)
  - Questionnaire Responses (Box 6)
  - Transcript (Box 6)
- Kappa Tau Alpha
  Kappa Tau Alpha is the national journalism honor society. The records from the University of Michigan chapter include correspondence from 1966-1981 with the society's national headquarters in Missouri, and project proposals, both for the individual student projects and for a special program held in March 1967 on "The Press and Criminal Procedure."
  - Alumni Directory Project (Box 6)
  - Minutes 1981 (Box 6)
  - National Correspondence 1966-1981 (Box 6)
  - Project Proposals 1967-1973 (Box 6)
- Women in Communications, Inc.
  The records of Women in Communications, Inc. (WICI) also reflect the involvement of Marion Marzolf. The local records date from 1970 to 1981, the period for which Marzolf was faculty advisor to the group. WICI is a national professional organization for people working in the various branches of the media and for journalism and communications students. The organization was founded as Theta Sigma Phi at the University of Washington in 1909. In 1926, the Alpha Theta Chapter was established at the University of Michigan. In 1972, the name was changed to Women in Communications, Inc., and men were formally admitted as organization members. The records in this series include files kept on the Michigan chapter by the national office (1935-1974), which were returned to Michigan after being microfilmed, and local files kept between 1970-1981. The local files include newsletters, minutes, agendas and flyers as well as correspondence between Marzolf and ex-students discussing the difficulties faced by women entering the field of journalism. The file on the 50th anniversary of WICI in 1976 contains particularly interesting descriptions by early women journalists of their experiences in the 1930s, 1940s and 1950s.
  - Constitution and Bylaws (Box 6)
  - National Records (includes correspondence, reports, etc.)
    - 1935-1939 (Box 6)
    - 1940-1949 (Box 6)
    - 1950-1955 (Box 6)
    - 1956-1960 (Box 6)
    - 1960-1964 (Box 6)
    - 1965-1968 (Box 6)
    - 1968-1974 (Box 6)
    - 1974-1975 (Box 6)
  - Local Records
    - Activity and End-of-Year Reports 1970-1981 (Box 7)
    - Historical File 1926-1981 (includes clippings, programs, etc.) (Box 7)
    - Newsletter and Minutes 1971-1980 (Box 7)
    - 1972-1973 (Box 7)
    - 1973-1974
      - General File (Box 7)
      - Regional Meeting March 1974 (Box 7)
    - 1974-1975 (Box 7)
    - 1975-1976
      - General File (Box 7)
      - 50th Anniversary Celebration February 1976 (Box 7)
    - 1976-1977 (Box 7)
    - 1977-1978 (Box 7)
    - 1978-1979 (Box 7)
    - 1979-1980 (Box 7)
    - 1980-1981 (Box 7)
- Chairman's Records 1949-1986
  - Correspondence File 1964-1985